Leah: If a child or young person
suffers any risk factors or starts
to show signs of distress, families,
communities and schools should support
them to cope better with the challenges
that life throws at them and try to be
there to listen to them when needed.
Rhiannon: Schools can often play a
critical role in giving young people
the skills they need to form strong
interpersonal relationships, which
will support resilience such as
buddy systems, peer to peer support
networks, and anti-bullying initiatives.
Leah: Schools that promote strong
social relationships and teach
practical coping skills, are likely
to have more resilient pupils, who
are able to learn more effectively.
Schools as well as families and friends
can help young people to learn how to
regulate their emotions, solve problems
and help them plan things that might help
them cope better when life gets tough.
Rhiannon: A child or young person can
help themselves, by keeping a diary to
aid focus on more positive memories.
They can also keep busy doing
things they enjoy, such as sports,
music or drama, and try and stay
away from the sources of stress.
Once the risk factors have been recognised
and understood by all concerned, they can
then be addressed, and the child or young
person can be better supported to maintain
good mental health and well-being.